hello and welcome to our lecture on computer architecture now to some degree
that might seem like a contradiction in terms because the whole name of the
course is computer architecture but we're kind of at the point where we have
gotten to the level where we've built up enough basic stuff to really start
talking about computer architecture like what's a central processing unit we know
what gates are we're going to start with the gates we're not going to worry about
transistors we're not going to worry about tubes we're not going to worry about slide
rules and then we're going to just go from there actually for me this phase is a
little more comfortable I was never a computer engineer or electrical
engineer and I kind of understand transistors and so that first half was
kind of fun for me to do a bunch of research for you and share with you what
I thought was important about transistors and tubes etc but now we're
going to start with gates what can we do with an and gate and or gate not gate
exclusive or etc first we're going to learn how to start adding numbers because
calculation and multiplication and addition are important what about the
full adders and half adders we have to learn about number representation how do
computers represent numbers base 2 base 10 and hexadecimal then we're going to
figure out how we actually store data using gates to store data we'll learn
about latches and flip-flops and once we start getting larger and more
complicated circuits we're starting to talk about delay and speed and clock
rate and all those kinds of things and then we'll start thinking about how you
build a computer that can execute programs machine code where you write
software in zeros and ones and then ultimately we'll take a look at how
CPUs are put together the architecture of CPUs so we often start with computer
architecture to talk about the whole computer like there's there's up things
like motherboards let me let me give you a close-up view of a motherboard but
actually this really isn't just any old motherboard when I started teaching
programming back in 2008 this was the motherboard that I would pass around the
class this is from a desktop computer it's a I think it's probably like a 300
megahertz computer which is really slow I also passed around the CPU that went to
this so there's the CPU that went to this particular computer and and I
passed it around the class because I wanted people to feel I wanted them to
feel the the wires that come out of these things to get a sense of this is
all very electrical and I've been talking from the beginning of the course
to the level of this is all very electrical so if you look at the back
of this there are little tiny wires many of them going all like little streets
and chips are like buildings that are in in a neighborhood and the wires go
between them and the other thing I wanted people to do is like pass this
around it because you can't feel it here but these are kind of pointy little
things where the chips and connectors come through the board and they're
soldered together and that's where these connectors are connecting to these wires
and so I just wanted people to get a sense that inside of a computer there
was something and it was physical and it was a thing and like a CPU the CPU has
has little pins on it and I wanted people to touch the pins you can see
many people over the years have touched these pins and they're all bent up and
so here I used to pass around this memory chip and again this is all from
2008 so that people could get a physical feeling of what was inside of computers
doing all of this work so generally if you think about all those wires they
generally are taking a zero or one back and forth and that's the what we like
about gates and gates simplify the analogness of all circuits and make it
so that we can think of them digitally and so this is a slide from a lecture
that I created in 2008 where I basically said this is what a computer does it has
a central processing unit which processes instructions it has main
memory which is where the instructions and data are stored it has secondary
memory which is like disk drives where you save files and load data etc and
databases live on disk drives and then put output devices like keyboards and
mice and things like that and so the definitions that I used back then were a
central processing unit runs the program the CPU is programmed physically to
wonder what to do next it's not really smart but it is very very fast and we
program it to be smart right input devices like keyboard mouse and touch
screen output devices like the screen speakers printer DVD burner or whatever
main memories small fast temporary storage and secondary memory is the
larger more permanent storage that you can power cycle and not come off and so
this notion that central processing units are built to think about what next
means that we are inside the computer when we write software we live in the
main memory of the computer and our instructions feed the what next that the
CPU will see toward the end we'll understand with a fetch execute cycle
which is fetch what is it I'm supposed to do next I did that now grab the next
one that's the fetch execute cycle now we can program this in something like
say Python but really it's not it's really programmed in machine language
which is zeros and ones and by the end of this lecture in the beginning of the
next lecture you will be programming in zeros and ones believe me this this one
is a little difficult so you just take your time and
follow along with how this goes and so from the last lecture we really saw the
growth of transistors where we had 16 transistors on a little tiny circuit to
laying out hundreds and millions and billions of transistors on little tiny
chips and so with that we can create increasingly complicated processes now
the way this design process usually works and we did VLSI layout in the
previous lectures we tend not to do VLSI layout for modern computers we tend to
build reusable components like an adder or a latch or something like that and
then we wire those all together and then software takes our abstract design of
gates and latches that that think in terms of zeros and ones and components
like adders and multipliers and ripple carry adders etc and then turn that into
a transistor layout and some of the things that computer CPUs do are so
important like adding and multiplying and like little caches and registers that
we might tune the hardware layout and the transistors a little bit but in
general software does all of the work and takes our abstract design and turns
it into an optimal layout for our chip and then of course we use photolithography
so up next we're going to talk about how we use gates to add numbers again going
to the point where we have gates now how can we construct multiple gate circuits
that accomplish the kinds of things that microprocessors want to do